Guide to the James Weldon Johnson and Grace Nail Johnson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1890-1974; Series II; 22.18; (43 boxes)
  - Major Works
    - Saint Peter Relates an Incident: Selected Poems
      - Setting copy, corrected by author and editor, 1935 (Box 64, Folder 265-266)
        Complete draft includes typescript, autograph leaves, and clippings (mounted) from JWJ's Fifty Years and Other Poems.
      - Page proofs, corrected by editor, before 1935
      - Book jacket, 1935 (Box 64, Folder 267)
    - The Second Book of American Negro Spirituals
      - Preface and notes, holograph and setting typescript, signed and corrected, before 1926 (Box 65, Folder 268)
        Includes preliminary notes and drafts and setting typescript with author's corrections and publisher's editorial markings.
      - Preface, printed version, 1933
        See: Printed version, annotated
      - Music, printer's proof, corrected, before 1926 (Box 65, Folder 269-270)
      - Scrapbook of printed versions, reviews, publicity material, and other related material, 1926-1935 (Box 66, Folder 271-279)
  - Essays and Articles
    - "Ada Overton Walker," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 67, Folder 280)
      A brief biographical sketch.
    - "American Minorities, the Negro", undated
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 67, Folder 281-282)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 67, Folder 283)
      - Draft, typescript, with autograph note signed from Grace Nail Johnson concerning background, undated (Box 67, Folder 284)
    - "The American Negro and Horse Racing," draft, typescript, undated (Box 67, Folder 285)
    - "American Negro Baseball Players," draft, typescript, undated (Box 67, Folder 286)
    - "The American Negro Prize Fighter," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 67, Folder 287)
    - "American Negro Spirituals," printed version, The Standard, 1926 January (Box 67, Folder 288)
    - "And the Gods Laugh," drafts, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 67, Folder 289-290)
      Submitted to the editor of Life 's Short Story Contest.
    - [Empty folder], undated (Box 67, Folder 291)
    - "Beautiful Women", 1913-1918
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, 1918 (Box 67, Folder 292)
      - Drafts, typescript, corrected, 1913, undated (Box 67, Folder 293)
    - "Belle Case La Follette Believed in the Negro," printed version, The Progressive, circa 1931
    - "The Best Methods for Removing the Disabilities of Caste from the Negro," holograph, signed, undated (Box 67, Folder 294)
      Prize-winning essay written as a student at Atlanta University.
    - "Bob Alley Cole," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 67, Folder 295)
    - "By Decree of the Critics," draft, typescript, undated (Box 67, Folder 296)
      Short story submitted "To the Editor of Life 's Short Story Contest."
    - "Challenge," Foreword, draft, typescript carbon, 1934 (Box 67, Folder 297)
    - "Circumstantial Evidence," draft, holograph, undated (Box 67, Folder 298)
      Includes extensive notes for the poem, "The Rivals," later published in Fifty Years and Other Poems, and for his plays, "Circumstantial Evidence," "Sons and Daughters," and "Do You Believe in Ghosts?"
    - "Clarence Darrow as I Knew Him," draft, holograph, signed, corrected and printed version, Unity, 1938 (Box 67, Folder 299)
    - "Communism and the Negro"
      - "The Negro and His Brain Trust, " draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1935 (Box 67, Folder 300)
      - "The Negro and His Brain Trust," draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1935 (Box 67, Folder 301)
      - "The Negro and His Brain Trust," draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1935 (Box 67, Folder 302)
      - Printed version, New York Herald-Tribune, This Week, 1935 July 21
    - "The Contents of a Name - Mozart Jackson, Composer," draft, holograph, undated (Box 67, Folder 303)
      Introduction to a story.
      Includes a note for lyrics "Love You Little Gal," on verso of first leaf.
    - "The Creative Negro," proof, corrected, undated (Box 67, Folder 304)
    - "Destiny of the Human Race," draft, holograph, signed, corrected, undated (Box 67, Folder 305)
    - "Detroit," printed version, The Crisis, 1926 July (Box 67, Folder 306)
    - "The Dilemma of the Negro Author"
      - Draft, holograph, signed, corrected, circa 1928 (Box 67, Folder 307)
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1928 (Box 67, Folder 308)
      - Printed version, The American Mercury, 1928 December (Box 67, Folder 309)
    - "Dyer Anti-Lynching Bill," draft, typescript and holograph notes, circa 1921 (Box 67, Folder 310)
      Background notes and statistics concerning the Dyer Anti-lynching Bill, introduced before U.S. Congress, 1921 April 11.
    - "Excess Patriotism", 1911
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, 1911 (Box 68, Folder 311)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, signed, corrected, 1911 (Box 68, Folder 312)
      - Draft, typescript, titled "The Evils of Excess Patriotism", undated (Box 68, Folder 313)
    - "The Gentleman's Agreement and the Negro Vote," printed version, The Crisis, 1924 October (Box 68, Folder 314)
    - "Heroes -- Virtuous vs. Villainous," draft, holograph, undated (Box 68, Folder 315)
    - "Horse Sense," drafts, typescripts and typescript carbons, corrected, 1911 (Box 68, Folder 316)
    - "How to Understand and Enjoy Negro Spirituals," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 68, Folder 317)
    - "The Intemperance Question," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1913 (Box 68, Folder 318)
    - "The International Factor in World Peace," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1934 (Box 68, Folder 319)
    - Introduction to "Southern Road," by Sterling Brown, drafts, holograph and typescripts, corrected, undated (Box 68, Folder 320)
    - "James (Jim) Bland," draft, typescript, undated (Box 68, Folder 321)
      Notes for a biographical sketch about Bland and others.
    - "Legal Aspects of the Negro Problem," printed version, The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1928 November (Box 68, Folder 322)
    - "Lynching: America's National Disgrace", printed version, Current History, 1924 January (Box 68, Folder 323)
    - "The Man Who Made Broadway Laugh," draft, holograph notes, undated (Box 68, Folder 324)
    - "Negro American Poets and Poetry"
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1934 (Box 68, Folder 325)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, circa 1934 (Box 68, Folder 326)
        Concerning African-American poets from 1760 through Langston Hughes.
    - "The Negro in American Life."
      - "Contributions of the Negro to American Life", draft, typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1936 (Box 68, Folder 327)
      - Printed version, World Outlook, 1936 November 14 (Box 68, Folder 328)
    - "The Negro's Creative Genius", printed version, The Christian Plea, undated (Box 68, Folder 329)
    - "The Negro and the Economic Crisis", printed version, The New Humanist, 1934 March-April (Box 68, Folder 330)
    - "Negro Folk Songs and Spirituals", printed version, The Mentor, 1929 February (Box 68, Folder 331)
    - "A Negro Looks at Politics"
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1929 (Box 68, Folder 332-333)
      - Printed version, The American Mercury, 1929 September (Box 68, Folder 334)
    - "A Negro Looks at Race Prejudice," printed version, The American Mercury, 1928 May (Box 68, Folder 335)
    - "Negro Poets and Their Poetry," draft, holograph notes, undated (Box 68, Folder 336)
      Leaves numbered A-H on perforated half sheets, bound in signed notebook.
    - "Negro Progress Since Emancipation"
      - Draft, holograph, signed, corrected, circa 1934 (Box 68, Folder 337)
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1934 (Box 68, Folder 338)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1934 (Box 68, Folder 339)
    - "A Negro Youth Movement," draft, typescript, undated (Box 68, Folder 340)
    - "New Songs for a New Day," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 68, Folder 341)
    - The New York Age
      - "Memorandum for Agreement," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1915 (Box 68, Folder 342)
        Agreement for the development of a subscription plan and other employment arrangements between Johnson and Fred R. Moore of the The New York Age.
      - Clippings of articles, 1914 October - 1915 February (Box 68, Folder 343)
      - Clippings of articles, 1915 March -1916 October (Box 69, Folder 344-347)
      - Clippings of articles, 1916 November -1918 June (Box 70, Folder 348-351)
      - Clippings of articles, 1918 June -1920 February (Box 71, Folder 352-357)
      - Scrapbook of clippings "Views and Reviews", 1920 January 3 - 1923 June 23
      - Scrapbook of clippings "Views and Reviews", 1922 October 7 - 1923 July 14
      - Scrapbooks of clippings "Views and Reviews" arranged by subject, 1923 January 6 - 1923 July 25 (Box 72, Folder 358-360)
      - The New York Age Scholarships
        - Advertisement drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected and printed version, circa 1915 (Box 73, Folder 361)
          Drafts of advertisement for a scholarship and premium plan sponsored by the The New York Age.
        - Correspondence, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, 1915 (Box 73, Folder 362)
          Letters to be sent to the presidents of Negro colleges and to members of the Scholarship Committee describing the scholarship program.
    - "Night Clubs," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 73, Folder 363)
    - "Notes on Concerns and Problems of the Negro," drafts, holograph and typescript notes, undated (Box 73, Folder 364)
      On the topics of migration, NAACP, miscellaneous statistics, etc.
    - "Notes on Early African Civilization," drafts, holograph, signed, undated (Box 73, Folder 365)
      Includes a brief bibliography.
    - "Notes on Humanitarian Subjects," holograph, undated (Box 73, Folder 366)
      On the topics of happiness, religious feeling, etc.
    - "The Origin of the 'Barber Chord,'" printed version, The Mentor, 1929 February (Box 73, Folder 367)
    - "The Origin and Development of Ragtime," draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 73, Folder 368)
    - "The Origin of Sin," drafts, typescript, corrected, signed, 1918 (Box 73, Folder 369)
      Contains two typescripts. The first written in Corinto, Nicaragua and marked "O.K. A" and the second dated New York, 1918.
    - "The Origin of the Spirituals," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1931 (Box 73, Folder 370)
      Published in The Classmate 1931 October. Written at the request of Aldred D. Moore in his correspondence with Johnson (1931 January 13 - March 14).
    - "Packer 63," holograph plot synopsis, undated (Box 73, Folder 371)
    - "The Passing of Poetry," drafts, typescript, 1911-1913 (Box 73, Folder 372)
    - "Paul Dunbar," drafts, typescript, signed and corrected, undated (Box 73, Folder 373)
    - "The Place of the Negro in American Life," draft, typescript carbon, 1929 April 22 (Box 73, Folder 374)
      Sent to F.A.R. Peterson, editor of the London Times.
    - "Presence of Mind," drafts, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 73, Folder 375)
      Submitted to the editor of Life Magazine 's Short Story Contest.
    - "Race Prejudice and the Negro Artist," printed version, Harper's Monthly Magazine, 1928 November (Box 73, Folder 376)
    - "A Ragtime Author," holograph notes, undated (Box 73, Folder 377)
    - "Single Blessedness or Double Bliss," drafts, typescript, signed and corrected, undated (Box 73, Folder 378)
    - "Sons and Daughters," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 73, Folder 379)
    - "To a Defeated Warrior Who I Believe Had Ideals and Tried to Live Up to Them," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 73, Folder 380)
    - "To the Editor of the [New York] Times," draft, holograph signed and corrected, undated (Box 73, Folder 381)
    - "To What Extent Do You Think American Negroes Should Interest Themselves in Abyssinia?" draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 73, Folder 382)
      Johnson's reply to the question.
    - "The Value of the College Bred Man to the Community," draft, holograph signed, undated (Box 73, Folder 383)
      In a tablet.
    - "Visit to Southern Newspaper Editors," draft, holograph, undated (Box 73, Folder 384)
      Diary of author's interviews with newspaper editors, 14-25 November.
    - "The War Catechism," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 73, Folder 385)
      Written while living in Jacksonville, Florida.
    - "What America Owes to the Negro"
      - "The Negro's Contribution to America," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1923 (Box 73, Folder 386)
      - Printed version, Our World, 1923 August 5 (Box 73, Folder 387)
    - "Why Charles E. Hughes Should Be Elected," printed version, The Hamiltonian, 1916 November (Box 73, Folder 388)
    - "Why Latin America Dislikes the United States," draft, typescript carbon, 1913 September 30 (Box 73, Folder 389)
    - "Woman Suffrage," draft, typescript, undated (Box 73, Folder 390)
    - "Words and Clothes," drafts, typescripts, corrected and signed, 1911 (Box 73, Folder 391)
  - Single Poems
    - "And God Was There Sitting on His Throne..." draft, holograph with notes, undated (Box 73, Folder 392)
    - "Brer Rabbit, You's de Cutes' of 'Em All," printed version, Fiction Parade, 1936 September (Box 73, Folder 393)
    - "Change," and "Requiem," draft, typescript with author's query, undated (Box 73, Folder 394)
    - "Class Poem," Atlanta University Class of 1894, draft, holograph, circa 1894 (Box 73, Folder 395)
    - "The Departing Ship," draft, typescript, undated (Box 73, Folder 396)
      Corinto, Nicaragua
    - "Futility," drafts, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 73, Folder 397)
    - "Helene," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 74, Folder 398)
    - "The Insult," drafts, typescript, corrected and signed with initials, undated (Box 74, Folder 399)
    - "Life," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 74, Folder 400)
    - "Life and Death," draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 401)
    - "Man," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 402)
      Originally intended for inclusion in his Fifty Years and Other Poems, but not used.
    - "The Miser," drafts, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 403)
    - "Moods," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 404)
    - "Mother Night," draft, holograph, 1908 December (Box 74, Folder 405)
      Dated December 1908, Puerto Bello [Venezuela].
      With earlier working draft on verso of leaf.
      First published in his Fifty Years and Other Poems.
    - "A Passing Melody," draft, typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 406)
    - "Plainte," draft, typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 407)
    - "The River," drafts, typescript and typescript carbons, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 408)
    - "A Texas Carnival," draft, typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 409)
    - "Three Addresses," drafts, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 410)
      One draft includes subtitle, "to the white south, to the black south."
    - "To Louie," draft, typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 411)
      With holograph title, "The tail of a kitten."
    - "The Young Warrior," printed version, The Citizen, 1915 September (Box 74, Folder 412)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 74, Folder 413)
      Holograph note: "Short Version".
  - Song Lyrics
    - "Answer to prayer," draft, typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 414)
      Original published in his Fifty Years and Other Poems.
    - "Auto-Mo-Bills," draft, typescript carbons, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 415)
      Original title, "My Automobile."
    - "Beautiful Daughters of Eve," drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, undated (Box 74, Folder 416)
    - "Beauty That Is Never Old," drafts, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 417)
      Version of a poem originally published in his Fifty Years and Other Poems.
    - "Everybody," drafts, typescript carbons, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 418)
      Lyrics of a song written for Bert Williams.
    - "Helen Winter," drafts, typescripts and typescript carbons, 1914, undated (Box 74, Folder 419)
      Includes "Version A," "Version B," "Version C," and "Version D" with author's corrections.
    - "Henry Hawkins," drafts, typescripts and typescript carbons, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 420)
      Includes version with the title, "'enry 'awkins," and text in dialect, and version with title "Henry, If You Ever Come Back to Me"
    - "Home Ain't No Place for Me," draft, holograph, undated (Box 74, Folder 421)
      Lyrics, with monologue after first chorus.
    - "Kongo King," draft, typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 422)
    - "Lazy," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 423)
      Originally published in his Fifty Years and Other Poems.
    - "Listen to Me in a Very Different Way," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 424)
    - "Mobile Mardi Gras," draft, typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 425)
    - "On the Sunny Side of the Mason-Dixon Line," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 426)
    - "Shoo-Fly Regiment," draft, typescript carbon, 1904-1905 (Box 74, Folder 427)
      Written with Bob Cole.
    - "That's the Kind of Love I Love," drafts, typescripts and typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 428)
    - "Turn On the Love Light," drafts, holograph, signed and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 429)
    - "Vanity Fair," drafts, typescript carbon, undated (Box 74, Folder 430)
    - "What Did You Do To Me?" draft, typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 431)
    - "When the Twilight Shades Are Softly Falling," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 74, Folder 432)
    - "Where Was I?" draft, holograph, undated (Box 74, Folder 433)
    - Other lyrics, undated (Box 74, Folder 434)
      Includes: "Can't you play something we can one-step to?," "I ain't seen yo' name in history," "I've got a disposition like a rubber ball," "I'll love you honey when your money's gone but I will not be with you," "I wonder where she learned," "Lazy love," "Love always finds a way, "Oh, you joy child," "The pathway of love," "Peter and Wendy (duet)," "Peggy is a New Yorker now," "Play a rag," "The Postillion-Ragtime started in the ark," "Summer love," "See I am only a maiden...," "Tell me what's your name," "Three questions," "A toast," "When first we met," and "Yu-nu-san."
    - Notes, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 74, Folder 435)
  - Dramatic Works
    - "Aunt Mandy's Chicken Dinner," draft, typescript, corrected, 1914 (Box 74, Folder 436)
    - "The Black Billionaire," draft, typescript, 1914 (Box 74, Folder 437)
      Alternative title: "He Makes an Investment"
    - "The Czar of Czam"
      - Script, draft, typescript, circa 1902-1905 (Box 74, Folder 438)
      - Lyrics, draft, typescript, circa 1902-1905 (Box 74, Folder 439)
    - "Do You Believe In Ghosts?"
      - Draft, typescript, 1914 (Box 74, Folder 440)
        "A Darky Comedy."
        Includes story synopsis, scene plot and script with an autograph note dating delivery of work to Lubin (1914 July 9)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, circa 1914 (Box 74, Folder 441)
      - Draft, typescript, circa 1914 (Box 74, Folder 442)
        Version "Reconstructed by J. A. Murphy" with notes by Johnson.
    - "Down the Nile," draft, holograph, undated (Box 74, Folder 443)
      Synopsis for a play about a great composer.
    - "El Presidente or The Yellow Peril, A Comic Opera," drafts, typescript and holograph and notes, undated (Box 75, Folder 444-446)
    - "The Engineer"
      A drama in one act.
      - Draft, typescript, in blue cover, undated (Box 75, Folder 447)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 75, Folder 448)
        Includes ANS inscribed on title page by Johnson.
        Cover sheets are on stationery of J. Rosamond Johnson.
    - "The Fakir"
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 75, Folder 449)
        Libretto for comic opera in three acts, written with Bob Cole, based on his early unproduced opera "Tolosa."
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 75, Folder 450)
    - "The Fortune Hunter," synopsis, holograph, circa 1909 (Box 75, Folder 451)
    - "Helene," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 75, Folder 452)
      A Romantic Operetta in Three Scenes.
      Music by Will Marion Cook.
      Alternative titles: "La Belle Helene" or "The Call of the Blood"
    - "Ignacio," draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 75, Folder 453)
      Possible translation
    - "Kongo King," draft, typescript and holograph, undated (Box 75, Folder 454)
      Possibly draft fragments for "The Cannibal King"
    - "The Man and the Maid," draft, holograph, undated (Box 75, Folder 455)
      Notes for a musical play, including a partial synopsis and cast of characters, on verso of a note is author's memo concerning a romantic operetta about slaves.
    - "Tolosa, or the Royal Document; a Comic Opera"
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, circa 1899 (Box 75, Folder 456)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1899 (Box 75, Folder 457)
        Lacking pages 18, 19, 25, and Act III.
        Includes stage layout diagrams. Additions, corrections, and revisions used in "The Fakir".
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1899 (Box 75, Folder 458)
        Complete copy with a few notations and additions. With an ANS by J. Rosamond Johnson concerning the origins of the opera.
      - Notes and fragments, circa 1899 (Box 75, Folder 459)
    - "Uncle Tom's Cabin, an Operatic Cantata: Synopsis of Cantata," draft, typescript, undated (Box 75, Folder 460)
    - "Why Don't You Get a Lady of Your Own?" draft, typescript, undated (Box 75, Folder 461)
      "A Darkey Comedy by Weldon Johnson"
      Synopsis of scenes.
    - Untitled, draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 75, Folder 462)
      Contains draft outline and script for Act 1 of a play with Uncle Remus.
  - Addresses
    - "Africa at the Peace Table and the Descendants of Africans in Our American Democracy," printed version, undated (Box 76, Folder 463)
    - "American Democracy and the Negro", undated
      - Draft, typescript, annotated, undated (Box 76, Folder 464)
        Address from NAACP Field Secretary Notebook.
      - Draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 76, Folder 465)
    - "American Negro Poets and Poetry", 1924 April 10
      Address delivered at Howard University.
      - Draft, typescript, 1924 April 10 (Box 76, Folder 466)
        From NAACP Field Secretary Notebook.
      - Draft, typescript, 1924 April 10 (Box 76, Folder 467)
    - "The American Occupation of Haiti"
      Author's reading script of speech given at Commodore Hotel [New York?].
      Report of his investigation of the American occupation of Haiti for the NAACP.
      - Draft, typescript and holograph notes, circa 1920 (Box 76, Folder 468)
      - Report on Johnson's speech, typescript carbon, incomplete, circa 1920 (Box 76, Folder 469)
    - "The Art of Being Civilized", 1935 June 28
      Address at the Northwestern University Institute of Human Relations.
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1935 June 28 (Box 76, Folder 470)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, 1935 June 28 (Box 76, Folder 471)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1935 June 28 (Box 76, Folder 472)
    - "Bearers of Gifts to America", 1936 February 9
      Address given at Chicago University.
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1936 February 9 (Box 76, Folder 473)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, 1936 February 9 (Box 76, Folder 474)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, 1936 February 9 (Box 76, Folder 475)
    - "Bearers of Gifts to America," revision, 1938